Brainerd family papers
Connecticut Historical Society
Brainerd Family Papers
1750-1876
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Brainerd family.
0.50 linear feet (1 box)
Biographical Sketch
George Smith Brainerd (1792-1872) was a farmer and quarryman living in Haddam, Connecticut. For the town of Haddam, he served as treasurer, constable, and justice of the peace. In the late 1840s and 1850s, he was a practicing attorney, taking only a few cases, doing mostly probate work.
Scope and Content
The collection of more than 360 items includes the account book of George S. Smith; individual bills and receipts; correspondence; legal papers; and other material formerly in the possession of George S. Brainerd (GSB).
The account/day book (1839-1871) documents the building of Brainerd Academy, George S. Brainerd’s farm business (he made much of his money in renting out his animals and vehicles), and his legal business (clients included the Ecclesiastical Society of Haddam, the heirs of Calvin Thomas and Selden Brainerd, and the Pier Island Co.)
Individual papers of George S. Brainerd have been sorted, where possible, by his role (e.g. constable, JP, attorney). Brainerd’s papers are followed by items relating to immediate family: parents, uncles, wife and children. Of note is the divorce decree of GSB’s uncle Nehemiah, dated 1845.
Some of the items in the collection bear only a tenuous relationship to George S. Brainerd. Among these is a group of letters written by distant cousin Polly Brainerd of Enfield to her parents Mr. And Mrs. John Pierce of Millbury, Massachusetts. Within the Polly Brainerd correspondence is a single letter written by a Cemantha Horn to John Pierce detailing the last days and suicide of her husband. Attachments and summonses signed by other Haddam JPs are presumed to be GSB’s in his capacity as constable. The receipts of James Hazelton and one or more of the tax lists predate GSB and their connection to him remains a mystery.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Brainerd, George Smith, 1792-1872
Family Names
Brainard family.
Subjects
Justices of the Peace -- Connecticut -- Haddam.; Lawyers -- Connecticut -- Haddam; Taxation -- Connecticut -- Haddam; Municipal officials and employees -- Connecticut -- Haddam.
Geographic Names
Haddam (Conn.: Town) -- Politics and government.
Contents:
- Papers
  - GSB: Account book, 1839-1871 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - GSB: Bills, receipts, accounts, 1817-1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - GSB, constable: Papers, 1817-1823 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - GSB, justice of the peace: Papers, 1841-49, 1857-8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - GSB and brothers: Deeds, 1817-1869 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - GSB: Property insurance, 1854-1871 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - GSB, attorney: Probate clients, 1835-1853 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - GSB, attorney: Miscellaneous clients, 1840s-1850s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - GSB: Speech re Henry Clay (unsigned but in the hand of GSB), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - GSB et al: Research notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Extended Family: Eliakim and Lucy Brainerd (parents of GSB), 1816, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Extended Family: Nehemiah, John and Fisk Brainerd (uncles of GSB), 1807-1848 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Extended Family: Elizabeth Huntington Brainerd et al.(wife and children of GSB), 1876 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Extended Family: Polly Brainerd (Mrs. Jared Brainerd, nee Mary Pierce) (distant cousin of GSB), 1817-1827, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Other Brainerds (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Various Haddam JPs: Attachments, summonses, 1816-1842 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - James Hazelton, Haddam Town Treasurer, et al: Receipts, 1750-1789 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Haddam Tax lists (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fragments (Box 1, Folder 20)